We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
More than 10,000 articles
have been published on gluten
in medical journals—
intimidating even for me!
Today we have a
three part series
summarizing the best
available science on gluten.
In our first story, we look at
how we might prevent
the inflammation that occurs
from gluten-free diets.
Over the last decade or so,
there’s been a growing interest
in the medical literature
on plant-based eating,
beyond just exclusionary
terms like vegetarian or vegan.
Previous such studies
were somewhat limited
because they just split
people up into either
vegetarian or nonvegetarian,
excluding some or all animal foods,
but without taking into account
the quality of plant foods.
Vegans could be living off of
French fries, Oreos, and Coca-Cola.
Enter: “Changes in Plant-Based
Diet Quality and Total and
Cause-Specific Mortality,”
the first study to investigate
the associations between
changes in plant-based diet quality
and subsequent risk of death.
If you look at overall
plant-based diet scores,
the more you increase your
intake of any plant foods and
decrease your intake
of any animal foods,
the lower your risk of
death appears to fall,
but that’s because people
were adding healthy plant foods
like fruits and vegetables.
If you just look at people
who ate more processed,
sugary junk over time,
their mortality risk goes up,
the clinical implications
being that increasing intake
of healthy plant foods
and decreasing intake
of not just animal foods,
but also animal crackers,
could lower the future risk
of premature death.
Whereas just reducing the
intake of carbs in general,
cutting down not just
refined carbs and sugars,
but healthy high carb foods
like fruits and whole grains
is associated with
increased overall mortality,
which would correspond to years
of your life being cut short,
as well as the risk
of dying specifically
from heart disease,
stroke, and cancer.
Why are whole plant
foods so good for us?
Much of the benefit may be
mediated by our microbiome.
There are all sorts of things
threatening our good gut bugs,
like the over prescription
of antibiotics, however,
the only factor that has been
empirically shown to be important
is a diet low in microbiome-
accessible carbohydrates,
in other words prebiotics
like fiber and resistant starch
only found one place in
abundance, whole plant foods.
We went from high-MAC
diets to Big Mac diets
and may be suffering
the consequences.
Intake of dietary fiber, which is
the main source of MACs in the diet
is negligibly low compared
to how we evolved.
Such a low-fiber diet provides
insufficient food for our gut microbes,
starving ourselves of all the
wonderful things they produce for us.
A low-fiber diet is a key
driver of microbiome depletion,
and this loss is implicated
in the rampant increase
of chronic diseases that
now plague the modern world.
We evolved getting perhaps
a hundred grams of fiber a day.
Our gut bugs must
have been in heaven.
How do you get even close to that?
A cup of fruit may only have about
3 grams, a cup of
vegetables, 5 grams.
Why so little? Because
fruits and vegetables
are like 80 to 90 percent water.
One has to go to the drier plant
foods to really scale it up,
like beans, at 15 grams,
or intact grains like barley,
over 30 grams per cup.
But many people are avoiding
common grains these days,
like wheat barley and
rye due to gluten,
but there is a dark side
of gluten-free diets.
Now, if you have a condition
like celiac disease,
then you absolutely have to
avoid gluten, but if not,
the downsides include the potential
for nutritional deﬁciencies,
like not getting enough
fiber, and toxic compounds,
for example the
accumulation of heavy metals
in people on gluten-free diets.
Those following a gluten-free
diet had signiﬁcantly increased
blood mercury levels, more
arsenic flowing through their systems.
The arsenic is likely due to
increased rice consumption because
rice is a major ingredient
in gluten-free foods,
but you can certainly choose
other grains like sorghum—
that’s my favorite rice substitute.
And the higher mercury may
just be because people eating
gluten-free diets were tending
to eat more fish for some reason.
But the reason that 10 out of
10 of those without celiac disease
or a recognized gluten sensitivity
following a gluten-free diet
experienced a pro-inﬂammatory
gastrointestinal environment
is likely due to starving
your microbial self,
not getting enough prebiotics,
not getting enough fiber
because you’re avoiding
grains like wheat.
So, whatever diet you
choose for whatever reason,
make sure you’re
getting enough fiber.
In our next story, we look at how
the effects of gluten on our health
have been debated for
more than 30 years.
In 1980, researchers in England
reported a series of women
who suffered from chronic diarrhea
that resolved on a gluten-free diet,
yet did not have evidence of celiac disease,
the autoimmune disorder associated
with gluten intolerance.
The medical profession was skeptical
at the time, and even 30 years later,
so much so, that much like patients
who had irritable bowel syndrome,
patients claiming non-celiac gluten sensitivity
were commonly referred to psychiatrists
because they were believed to have
an underlying mental illness.
Psychological testing of such patients,
however, found no evidence
that they were suffering from some
kind of psychosomatic hysteria.
The medical profession has a history of
dismissing diseases as all in people’s heads—
PTSD, ulcerative colitis, migraines,
ulcers, asthma, Parkinson’s, MS.
Despite resistance from the prevailing
medical community at the time,
these health problems have
subsequently been confirmed
to be credible physiologically-based disorders
rather than psychologically-based confabulations.
On the flip side, the Internet is rife with
unsubstantiated claims about gluten free diets,
which has spilled over into the popular press
to make gluten the diet villain du jour
with claims like ‘17 million
Americans are gluten sensitive.’
However, it must be remembered
that this is also ‘big business.’
When literally billions of dollars are
at stake, it’s hard to trust anybody,
so as always, best to stick to the science.
What sort of evidence do we have for the existence
of a condition presumed to be so widespread?
Not much.
The evidence base for such claims
was unfortunately very thin
because we didn’t have
randomized controlled trials
demonstrating that the entity even exists.
The gold-standard for confirming non-celiac
gluten sensitivity requires a gluten-free diet,
followed by a double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled food challenge.
Like you give someone a muffin
and they’re not told
if it’s a gluten free muffin or gluten filled
muffin – to control for placebo effects –
and see what happens.
The reason this is necessary is
because when you actually do this,
a number of quote-unquote “gluten-sensitive”
patients don’t react at all to disguised gluten,
and instead react to the gluten-free
placebo, so it truly was in their heads.
But we never had that kind of
level of evidence until 2011,
when a double-blind, randomized placebo-
controlled trial was published,
which tested to see if patients complaining
of irritable bowel type symptoms,
who claimed they felt better on a gluten free
diet – despite not having celiac disease –
actually could tell if they
were given gluten free bread
and muffins or the
gluten-containing bread and muffins.
They started out gluten-free
and symptom-free for two weeks
and then they were challenged
with the bread and muffins.
Here’s what happened to the 15
patients who got the placebo,
meaning they started out on a gluten-free
diet and continued on a gluten-free diet.
They got worse.
Just the thought that they may be eating
something that was bad for them
made them feel all crampy and bloated.
This is what’s called a nocebo effect.
The placebo effect is when you give someone
something useless and they feel better.
The nocebo effect is when you give someone
something harmless and they feel worse.
But the small group that got
the actual gluten felt worse still.
So, they concluded, this non-celiac
gluten intolerance may actually exist.
It was a small study, though,
and even though they claimed
the gluten-free bread and
muffins were indistinguishable,
maybe at some level the patients
could tell which is which.
So in 2012, researchers in
Italy took 920 patients that
had been diagnosed with
non-celiac gluten sensitivity
and put them to the test
with a double-blinded wheat
challenge by giving them not bread and muffins,
but capsules filled with
wheat flour or filled with
placebo flour, kind of a placebo
powder – no flour at all.
And more than two-thirds
failed the test, like they
got worse on the placebo or better on the wheat.
But of those that passed,
there was a clear benefit
to staying on the wheat-free diet, confirming the
existence of a non-celiac wheat sensitivity.
Now note they said wheat sensitivity,
not gluten sensitivity.
Gluten itself may not be
causing gut symptoms at all.
See, most people with wheat sensitivity
have a variety of other food sensitivities.
Two thirds are sensitive to
cow’s milk protein as well,
then eggs were the most common culprit after that.
So if you put people on a diet low in
common triggers of irritable bowel symptoms
and then challenge them with gluten,
there’s no effect.
Same increase in symptoms with high gluten,
low gluten, or no gluten, calling into question
the very existence of
non-celiac gluten sensitivity.
Interestingly, despite
being informed that avoiding
gluten wasn’t apparently doing
a thing for their gut symptoms,
many participants opted to
continue following a gluten-free
diet as they just subjectively
described “feeling better,”
so the researchers wondered
if avoiding gluten might
be improving the mood of
those with wheat sensitivity,
and indeed, short-term exposure to gluten appeared
to induce feelings of
depression in these patients.
But whether non-celiac gluten
sensitivity is a disease of the mind
or the gut, it is no longer a
condition that can be dismissed.
Finally today, how common
is gluten sensitivity?
Are there benefits to gluten?
Why does the medical profession
explicitly advise against people
who might suspect they
may be gluten intolerant
from just going on
a gluten-free diet?
Let’s find out.
Until only a few years ago, almost
the whole of the scientific world
maintained that the wheat protein gluten
would provoke negative effects
only in people with rare conditions such
as celiac disease or wheat allergies,
but by the early part of 2013,
it was largely becoming accepted
that some nonceliac patients could suffer
from gluten or wheat sensitivity.
And indeed a consensus panel of
experts now officially recognizes
three gluten-related conditions, wheat allergy,
celiac disease, and gluten sensitivity.
So what percent of the population
should avoid wheat?
Although 1 in a thousand may have a wheat allergy,
nearly 1 in a 100 may have celiac disease,
and it appears to be on the rise, though there’s
still less than about 1 in 10,000 chance
Americans will get diagnosed
with celiac in a given year.
How common is wheat sensitivity?
Our best estimate at this point is in that same
kind of general range, slightly higher than 1%,
but still that’s potentially millions of
people who may have been suffering for years
who could have been cured
by simple dietary means,
yet went unrecognized and unhelped
by the medical profession.
Although gluten sensitivity continues
to gain medical credibility,
we still don’t know how it works, or
how much gluten can be tolerated,
if it’s reversible or not and what
the long-term complications
might be of not sticking to the diet.
Considering the lack of knowledge,
maybe people with gluten sensitivity
should be trying to reintroduce gluten
back into their diet every year
to see if it’s still causing problems.
The reason health professionals don’t
want to see people on gluten-free diets
unless absolutely necessary is
that for the 98% of people
people that don’t have
gluten issues, whole grains—
including the gluten grains -
wheat, barley and rye—
are health promoting, linked
to the reduced risk of
coronary heart disease, cancer, diabetes,
obesity and other chronic diseases.
Just like, because some
people have a peanut allergy,
doesn’t mean that everyone
should avoid peanuts.
There is no evidence to suggest
that following a gluten-free diet
has any significant benefits
in the general population.
Indeed, there is some evidence to suggest that
a gluten-free diet may adversely affect
gut health in those without celiac disease
or gluten sensitivity or allergy.
They’re talking about this study that
found that a month on a gluten-free diet
may hurt our gut flora
and immune function,
potentially setting those on gluten-free
diets up for an overgrowth
of harmful bacteria in
their intestines. Why?
Because, ironically, of the beneficial
effects of the very components
wheat sensitive people have problems
with—like the FODMAP fructans
that act as prebiotics and
feed our good bacteria,
or the gluten itself,
which may boost immune function.
Less than a week of added
gluten protein significantly
increases natural killer cell activity,
which could be expected to improve our body’s
ability to fight cancer and viral infections.
High gluten bread improves
triglyceride levels better
than regular gluten bread,
as another example.
Ironically, one of the greatest threats of
gluten-free diets may be the gluten itself.
Self-prescription of a gluten-free diet may
undermine our ability to pick up celiac disease,
the much more serious form
of gluten intolerance.
The way we diagnose celiac is
by looking for the inflammation
caused by gluten in
celiac sufferers,
but if they haven’t been eating a lot
of gluten, we might miss the disease.
Hence, rather than being on
a gluten-free diet,
we want celiac suspects to be
on a gluten-loaded diet.
We’re talkin’ 4-6 slices of gluten packed bread
a day, every day for at least a month,
so we can definitively
diagnose the disease.
Why does it matter so much to get a formal
diagnosis if you’re already on a gluten-free diet?
Well, it’s a genetic disease so
you’ll know to test the family,
but most importantly many people on gluten-free
diets are not actually on gluten-free diets.
Even 20 parts per million can be
toxic to someone with celiac.
Many on so-called gluten-free diets
inadvertently still eat gluten.
Sometimes there’s contamination
of gluten-free products,
so even foods labeled "gluten-free"
may still not be safe for celiac sufferers.
That’s why we need to know.
The irony, editorialized in
a prominent medical journal,
of many celiac patients not
knowing their diagnosis,
while millions of non-sufferers
banish gluten from their lives,
can be considered a
public health farce.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.